Ainsworth, Steven King; Papers apap347
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Steven King Ainsworth Papers
1993-2018
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap347
.33 cubic ft.
The Steven King Ainsworth Papers contain his artwork and writings, including "Heads Up" bulletins written by Ainsworth for prison inmates sentenced to life, life without parole, and their advocates.
Collection X
Biographical History
Steven King Ainsworth, currently incarcerated in California, was sentenced to death in 1980 for the murder of Seng Huynh and served two decades on Death Row in San Quentin. In 2001 the United States District Court for the Eastern District of California granted Ainsworth's habeas corpus petition vacating his capital sentence. Ainsworth is a published writer of fiction and non-fiction, and a self-taught artist whose work has been exhibited in the United States and internationally. His many publications include Words from the Row and essays or short stories in Undoing Time: American Prisoners in Their Own Words (2001), Writing for Their Lives: Death Row U.S.A. (2007), and Fourth City: Essays from the Prison in America (2014).
Scope and Contents
The Steven King Ainsworth Papers contain his artwork and writings, including "Heads Up" bulletins written by Ainsworth for prison inmates sentenced to life, life without parole, and their advocates. The bulletins contain advice for and background information about petitioning the Governors Office for clemency in the State of California, as well as news clippings of interest. The collection also contains correspondence and Ainsworth's applications for executive clemency including letters of support.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged alphabetically. There are no series.
Acquisition Information
Steven King Ainsworth donated his papers to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives in 2014, 2018, 2019, 2024 and 2025. The 2025 donation was sent care of Judith McAllister.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Criminal Justice and Prisons; Death Penalty; Steven King Ainsworth; Death row; Death Row inmates--California
- Application for Executive Clemency, Drafts and Final, 2018; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Application for Executive Clemency, Letters of Support, 2018; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "Cages" by Geogiann Lyga's and "California: Report from a Court" by Kay J. Bandell's and Correspondence, 2004 September (Box 1, Folder 3)
- California Penal Code Sections 4800-4813, 2017 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- California State Prison-Sacramento-Mailing Regulations with Correspondence, 2003 October (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence Addressed to Margo, 2002-2005 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence Addressed to Maria, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence from Bridget, 2004 January 12; 2004 October 03 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Drawing and Correspondence, 1993 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "Exiting Death Row Alive" Rough Draft with Correspondence, 2005 January 02 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "Heads Up," No. 1-8, 10-11, 2013; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "Heads Up" Supplement, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Lesson in Stupidity, 2010 January 25 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Letter to Governor Schwarzenegger Suggesting Policy Changes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- "Now is the Time", Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Review of California Law 43 McGeorge L. Rev. 747, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Review of an Exhibit and a Photo of Notre Dame Cathedral with Correspondence, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Writings by Steven King Ainsworth, 1996-1998; Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)